AI imposes super weird constraints on your code base.
And most code bases out there in the world
probably including yours are not ready.
Your code base way more than the prompt
that you used way more than your agents.md file
is the biggest influence on AI's output.
And if it's designed wrong,
it can cost you in a bunch of different ways.
It can mean that the AI doesn't receive feedback fast enough
so it doesn't know if what it changed
actually did what it intended.
It can find it super hard to make sense of things
and find files and work out even how to test things.
And finally, it can lead you into cognitive burnout
as you try to hold together AI and your code base
and patch it all up and keep everything in your mind.
And my thesis here is that software quality matters
more than ever.
In other words, how easy your code base is to change
makes a huge impact on how AI then goes and changes it.
And the stuff that we've known about software best practices
for 20 years still holds more true than ever.
And if you're interested in getting better at this stuff,
then check out my newsletter, AI hero.
I teach you all about AI coding,
but this is not for vibe coders.
This is for real engineers solving real problems.
And if that's you and you're not sure how to handle
these new tools, then you are gonna love it.
Now, let's imagine that this here is our code base.
Each one of these little squares represents a module
and this module might export some functionality,
it might export a function, might export some variables,
might export a component if it's like a, you know,
a reactor or a frontend thing.
I want you to imagine that this is the image of your code base
that you hold in your head.
Now, you might inside here have some vague groupings
of different functionality.
For instance, here you might have, let's say,
a thumbnail editor feature.
And all of these different modules contribute to that.
Over here you might have a little video editor feature
or something.
Down here is all the code related to authentication.
Up here is a bunch of crud forms for updating stuff,
maybe in a CMS.
And over here are a couple of example features
that I can't be bothered to think of examples for.
Now, this map that I've created here
of all of the located modules in this particular code base,
they're not actually reflected that much in the file system.
They're all really jumbled up together.
If I want to just grab, let's say, an export from this module
and import it down into this module, I can,
there's nothing stopping me.
And so what you might end up with is a bunch
of kind of disparate relationships between stuff
that doesn't actually relate to each other.
Now you as the developer understand the mental map
between all of these modules.
But what the AI sees when it first goes into your code base
is this.
It doesn't see all of the natural groupings
and all the natural relationships.
What it sees is a bunch of disparate modules
that can all import from each other.
That's because AI, when it jumps into your code base,
it has no memory, it has not experienced your code base
before.
It's like the guy from Memento who just steps in
and goes, okay, I'm here, what am I doing?
So my first assertion here is that you need to make sure
that the file system and the design of your code base
matches this internal map that you have off it.
This is because if you describe something
over in the video editor section
and you use it via a prompt,
then you want the AI to be able to find it easily.
The AI won't go in knowing every single function,
every single module, and what they're supposed to do
and how they link to each other.
And the best way I have found to do that
is with deep modules.
Now deep modules comes from this book here,
which is a philosophy of software design.
And the idea is that in order to make your system
easily navigable and easy to change
and also easy to test, is that you have a deep module
so lots of implementation control by a simple interface.
Well that looks like in terms of our graph
is instead of many, many small modules,
you end up with these big chunks of modules
with simple controllable interfaces.
And this means that any exports from these modules
have to come from that interface.
Now when I read that about deep modules,
I immediately thought about putting AI
in control of these modules
because this is an opportunity to introduce
a kind of seam into the code base.
I don't really care about what's happening inside here,
which is the implementation.
I just care about what's happening in the interface
because the interface, which is the publicly accessible API
of this module, I can carefully control
and I can apply my taste to and design.
And then the stuff inside here,
I can just delegate to an AI to control
and I can write tests that completely lock down
the module in terms of its behavior.
So these are not just deep modules
with simple interfaces, they're also gray box modules.
In other words, I don't actually need
to look inside these modules.
I can if I want to, if I want to influence their outcome
or if I need to apply some taste to the implementation
or I need to improve their performance or something,
but as long as the tests are good,
then I don't really need to care about what happens inside.
Now this has three massive benefits.
The first one is that I can make my code base
way more navigable.
Let's, for the sake of argument,
just call each of these services, right?
The video editor service, the thumbnail service, whatever.
If I document these each inside their own folder
and I have the publicly accessible interface,
kind of like a really obvious inner type section,
then the AI, when it's exploring my code base,
it can see all of these different services
on the file system.
It can read and understand the types that they export
before it actually looks at the implementation.
And then it can say, okay, I've seen the interface,
I understand what this does,
I don't need to look inside
because I can just trust what it's returning.
In other words, we've designed our code base
for progressive disclosure of complexity.
The interface sits at the top
and it just explains what the module does.
And then when we need to,
we can look inside the module and make changes to it
or look at it to understand its behavior more deeply.
The second one is that we reduce the cognitive burnout
of managing this code base.
Now as a user, I can just go, right,
I need something from, I don't know, this made up feature
or let's say the authentication bit over here.
Let's see what the public interface is.
Let's just grab that and use it.
And instead of needing to think about the interrelationships
between all of these modules,
I can just keep kind of like seven or eight lumps of stuff
in my head and go, okay, the AI manages the stuff inside that.
I only need to worry about designing the interfaces
and how they fit together.
Now this, of course, is still a million miles away
from vibe coding because you need to apply taste
at the boundaries of these modules.
You need to be really good at deciding, okay,
what goes into that module, what goes into that module.
And what you really want to avoid
are lots of little shallow modules,
which is kind of what we had up here, right?
Each of these modules is just like sure.
It's kind of interrelated and grouped together,
but really there are lots of tiny shallow modules
which are testable in these tiny units,
which are really hard to keep all in your head.
And so by simplifying the mental map of the code base,
we reduce cognitive burnout
that comes from managing this code base.
And again, this is nothing new.
This is a 20 year old software practice.
And the third one here, I mean,
I'm really just repeating myself,
but this is what we've been doing all along.
This is how good code bases have supposed to have been designed.
So what works here for humans is also great for AI.
We need to stop thinking about AI
as like this super powered developer
as like, you know, it's gonna reach AGI
and understand that it's got some weird limitations.
And the limitations that it has
are that it's a new starter in your code base.
So you need to make your code base
friendly and ready for new starters
because you're gonna be spawning like 20 new starters
every day here, probably more
just to look at your code base and make changes.
So that means the map of your code base
needs to be easily navigable
and it needs to be enforced by using these modules.
Now, some languages make this easier than others.
For instance, in TypeScript and JavaScript,
it's actually not that easy to make these services
make these modules sort of boundary in this way.
I want to give a quick shout out to Effect
because I posted a video on Effect a few months ago,
I'm actually using Effect way more than I did back then.
And it makes this kind of sort of seeming
modularizing of your code base really simple.
The final thing I want to say here
is that you need to be thinking about these modules
and how you're affecting them
and how you're designing the interfaces
in every coding session that you do.
That means right from the early planning stage
when you're writing your PRDs
or when you're turning your PRDs into implementation issues,
you need to be thinking about the modules
that you're affecting and the interfaces
and how you are going to test them
because tests and feedback loops are essential for an AI
because of course, they're essential
for a new starter joining the code base.
If you want a new starter to contribute effectively,
you need a well-tested code base
so they can see what their changes do as they ripple out.
So that's my rant for today.
Your code base is probably not ready for AI
because you're not using enough deep modules.
And instead you've got a web of interconnected
kind of shallow modules like this
which are really hard to navigate
and really hard to test and really hard to keep in your head.
Now if you dig this, then of course you will dig my newsletter
where we go more deeply into topics like this.
Thanks for watching folks.
What else do you think goes into making
a great code base for AI?
I really love this metaphor for deep modules
but I know it's not the only one going.
There are plenty out there.
Thanks for watching and I will see you very soon.
So when you're thinking about your code base with AI,
what are you thinking about?
What kind of 20-year-old books do you want to recommend?
Leave it in the comments.
It's the easiest way to keep up with all my stuff
and the link is below.